A Guide to the William Francis Brand Civil War Letters, 1856-1959 (bulk 1857-1866)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
William Francis Brand Civil War Letters, 1856-1959 (bulk 1857-1866)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11332
ca. 134 items (one Hollinger box).
This collection, 1856-1959 (bulk 1857-1866), chiefly consists of Civil War letters written by Confederate soldier William Francis Brand (1840-1932), Augusta County, Virginia, to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, his future wife and a Greenville, Augusta County resident. Brand was a private in Company E (the Augusta Grays), 5th Virginia Regiment, Stonewall Brigade, Army of Northern Virginia. Also present are notes, genealogical information, a 1959 news article concerning these letters, several letters from friends and relatives in Virginia and elsewhere, and photocopies of abbreviated typescripts and notes of selected Brand letters by the chairman of the Waynesboro Civil War Centennial Committee.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The William Francis Brand Civil War Letters were a gift to the Library from Mr. W. Brand McCaskill of Charlottesville, Virginia, September 27, 1997, and bear no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
According to Lee A. Wallace, Jr., 5th Virginia Infantry,(Lynchburg: H. E. Howard, 1988, page 99), and internal evidence in the collection, William Francis Brand was born August 31, 1840, in Augusta County, Virginia. By occupation he was a miller and enlisted (in Greenville) as a private in the Confederate Army, Company E, 5th Virginia Infantry, on April 18, 1861. He enlisted for the duration of the war, and during his military service was stationed or saw combat at Haynesville (July 2, 1861); First Manassas [First Bull Run] (July 21, 1861); furloughed because of the amputation of his big toe, March 16, 1863; Kernstown (March 23, 1862; his brother Tom was killed); Front Royal (May 23, 1862); McDowell (May 8, 1862); Winchester (May 25, 1862); Port Republic (June 9, 1862; struck in the hand by bouncing cannonball); Cold Harbor (June 27, 1862); Malvern Hill (July 1, 1862); Cedar Mountain (August 9, 1862); Winchester (June 13, 1863); Gettysburg (July 1-3, 1863); Seven Run? [Payne's House] (November 27, 1863; on detached duty to collect deserters in Augusta County, February 1864); the Wilderness (May 5-7, 1864; shot in the shoulder); Spotsylvania Court House (May 10-12, 1864); Winchester (September 19, 1864); Strasburg Junction (September 20, 1864; wounded in the thigh); and the Petersburg siege and retreat [April 2-6, 1865]. After the war Brand was a farmer and member Stonewall Jackson Camp of the United Confederate Veterans; he died in Lexington on May 25, 1932 and was buried at Tinkling Spring Presbyterian Church, Fisherville.
Scope and Content Information
Most of his letters, 1861-1867, are to his future wife Amanda C. Armentrout and accounts of camp life and members of his regiment and their families, local, state, and national events. Brand's letters sometimes reflect an often troubled relationship between the couple as they regularly accuse or apologize for supposed unfaithfulness, end and renew their relationship, pledge undying love and devotion to each other, set and postpone the date of their wedding (January 21, 1864, December 12, 1865, January 9, 1866, May 24, 1866, July 21, 1866). He also admits to a swearing problem and promises her that he will stop (April 5, 1866). He wrote his letters from a variety of Virginia cities, towns, counties and military camps including Brandy Station, Caroline County, Centreville, Charles Town, Essex County, Greenville, Harpers Ferry, Lexington, Liberty Mills, Madison County, Martinsburg, Morgan County, Nelson County, Orange County, Petersburg, Rockbridge County, and Winchester. Brand discusses illegal and underage voting by members of his regiment for secession (May 25, 1861); the battle of [First] Kernstown (April 6, 1862); the battle of [First] Winchester (May 29, 1862); his unhappy stay at a Nelson County hospital (August 29, 1862); thanks Armentrout for sending cheese (February 6, 1863); description of an operation on his big toe (May 23, 1863); using pokeroot ink to write his letters (October 11, 1863); a massive snowball fight between two groups of Confederate troops (March 24, 1864); the battles of Spotsylvania (May 16, 1864), Fisher's Hill (September 22, 1864), Cedar Creek (October 28, 1864), and Bentonville, North Carolina (March 22, 1865); and encountering barefooted Valley girls "awkward in their manners" (August 19, 1864).
Brand mentions or quotes prominent civilians and military personages in his letters including: Jefferson Davis [1808-1889], Jubal Early [1816-1894], Elmer Ellsworth [1837-1861], Richard Ewell [1817-1872], Richard Brooke Garnett [1817-1863], Joseph E. Johnston [1807-1891], Abraham Lincoln [1809-1865], James A. Longstreet [1821-1904], Prince Napoleon [Prince Napoléon-Jérôme, 1822-1891, born Napoléon-Joseph-Charles-Paul Bonaparte], John Pope [1822-1892], Robert Emmett Rodes [1829-1864], Jeb Stuart [1833-1864], James Alexander Walker [1832-1901], and Charles S. Winder [1829-1862]. Several identified members of various Confederate regiments and mutual friends and families are also mentioned or discussed by name. Brand's wartime letters are listed and described at the end of this guide.
Amanda C. "Kate" Armentrout, a resident of Greenville, Augusta County, and Brand's (postwar) wife was born on September 1 but the year is unknown (see her letter of September 1, 1867). There are several antebellum letters from her former schoolmate John P. Lightner [1841?-1862] who enlisted in Company I, 4th Virginia Infantry, during June 1861 and died of typhoid fever in February 1862 [James I. Roberston, 4th Virginia Infantry, second edition (Lynchburg, 1982), page 61]. According to the donor's genealogical notes "Family Record," Lightner later married Anne, Amanda's sister. Also present is a September 14, 1857, letter from John's brother George Pilson Lightner [1839-1925], later a member of the 52nd Virginia Infantry. John and George Lightner's letters describe student life at Brownsburg Academy and the Christian Creek School (both in Rockbridge County) and Washington College [later Washington and Lee University], Lexington, during 1856-1861. John describes war preparations in Lexington (May 18, 1861) and a flag presentation and speech by Governor John Letcher [1813-1884] and Company I's assignment as the headquarters guard for General Gustavus Woodson Smith [1822-1896] (October 31, 1861). William F. Brand mentions John Lightner in a June 23, 1861, letter. Lightner's letters are listed and described at the end of this guide.
Amanda Armentrout's 1859-1874 correspondents include various relatives and friends. A January 12, 1861, letter describes a taffy pull; there are also several letters from Robert B. Spillman, apparently a Confederate officer stationed at Chimborazo Hospital, Richmond, and later a Fredericksburg and Westmoreland County resident (December 28, 1864, January 12 and 29 and October 15, 1865, October 13, 1866). She addresses few of her letters to future husband William Francis Brand (whom she often addresses as "Willie): June 5, 1864, July 6, 23, 29, and August 17, 1866 (which includes a poem); she first addresses him as husband in her October 7, 1866, letter. Selected Armentrout letters are listed and described at the end of this guide.
Miscellaneous Brand family letters (1863, 1866-1867, 1873) include letters of William Francis Brand's brother Charles David Brand urging him to marry Armanda Armentrout (August 12 and November 25, 1866), an August 12, 1866, letter in which Charles discusses "a grand memorial" held at the Buckingham Female Institute [August 1, 1866] and attended by 500 persons "about two-thirds of that number lovely fair sex," and, a Confederate soldier's description of his wounding and capture at the battle of Gettysburg, November 11, 1863. A separate folder of miscellaneous materials and genealogical notes contains a 1959 news article about William and Amanda Brand ("Letters from Civil War Soldier Describe His Life As Member of Confederate Army," Waynesboro News-Virginian), a ca. 1925-1930 Standing Liberty Type Quarter Dollar, notes on the Brand letters by Colonel S. L. Denison, chairman, Waynesboro Civil War Centennial Committee, and a 1932 typescript excerpt from the minutes of Tinkling Spring Church regarding the death of Brand as its senior elder.
Organization
Letters of John P. Lightner to Amanda C. Armentrout, 1856-1861, 16 items
Correspondence of Amanda C. Armentrout, 1859-1866, 1867, and 1871-1874, 37 items
William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, 1861-1862, 20 items
WFB to Amanda C. Armentrout, 1863, 12 items
WFB to Amanda C. Armentrout, 1864-1865, 22 items
WFB to Amanda C. Armentrout, 1866-1867, 14 items
Miscellaneous Brand Family Letters, 1863, 1866-1867, and 1873, 6 items
Miscellaneous Materials and Genealogical Notes, ca. 1925, 1932, and 1959, n.d., 7 items
Contents List
- Letters of John P. Lightner to Amanda C. Armentrout 1856-1861
  - J. Pilson and J. Lightner to "Dear Schoolmate" 1856 Jan. 29
    Things are well at the Seminary [Christian Creek School]; are sending presents (two kisses)
  - [John P. Lightner, Christian Creek School] to "Dear Friend" Amanda C. Armentrout, Rose Dale] 1856 Dec. 24
    Unable to visit her during Christmas
  - J. T. Ly ? [John P. Lightner] "In My Seat," to "Dear Friend" ca. 1856
    "You must not think that I was insulted at all, never thought about such a thing as being insulted, Pshaw!"; religious sentiments
  - George Pilson Lightner (brother of John), Brownsburg, Rockbridge County, to "Miss Midie (Angus) 1857 Sept. 14
    Is boarding at the dwelling of Major Samuel Willson; describes one young lady and an old maid as both being "quite fascinating"; he and five friends dined on a watermelon for dinner; "I am very lonesome up her in one or two respects. 1st Is that Mr. Greer gives us too long lessons to learn. The other is, there are no nice ladies like you to home, & associate with"
  - JPL, Brownsburg Academy, Rockbridge County, to "Kind Friend" 1857 Sept. 28
    Student reminiscences about his former schoolmates at Christian's Creek
  - JPL, Fancy Hill, to "Dear Friend" 1858 Sept. 25
    Discusses his class work and general news; is only person to attend a local prayer meeting; religious sentiments; visited Natural Bridge "but it was not a very great curiosity to me"
  - JPL, Fancy Hill, to "Dear Friend" w/envelope addressed to ACA 1860 Jan. 15
    Has a cold; religious sentiments; unable to send his likeness "afraid I would break all the glass"
  - Angus, Green Bank, to "Dear Friend & Whilon Schoolmate" w/envelope addressed to Kate [Amanda Catherine?] Armentrout 1860 March 3
    "I have but one more week to teach in school"; mentions weddings, leap year, valentines; mentions a Miss Armentrout in Staunton
  - JPL, Washington College, to [ACA]: describes himself as "a little chap" 1860 April 7
  - [JPL], Washington College, to [ACA] 1860 Dec. 15
    "I expect to leave next Saturday or whip some of the Profs. As you know I am a great fighting character... We have a very quiet band of students this year, no drinking which was common last year"
  - JPL, Washington College, to [ACA] 1861 Feb. 16
    Is suffering a cold which delayed his reply to her previous letter; burden of correspondence with others and college duties
  - JPL, Washington College, to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1861 May 18
    Friendship; references to impending civil war and military preparations in Lexington
  - JPL, Stevens Camp, to ACA, w/envelope 1861 June 29
    Is stationed near Martinsburg, Berkeley County; reports peace rumors; says if he were Lincoln he would make peace
  - JPL, Fairfax Court House, to "My Dear Friend" [ACA] 1861 Oct. 31
    Governor John Letcher [1813-1884] yesterday presented state flags to every regiment and addressed the troops; his company as permanent headquarters guard for General Gustavus Woodson Smith [1821-1896]; camp life is fine
- Correspondence of Amanda C. Armentrout (selected) 1859-1866, 1867 & 1871-1874
  - Angus, Moffett's Creek, Virginia, to Miss Midie [Amanda C. Armentrout] 1859 March 14
    General news; "Why are you not going to school this winter? or have you got your diploma."
  - "From a friend," Arbor Hill, Virginia, to ACA w/envelope addressed to Miss A. C. Armentrout, Greenville, Virginia 1861 Jan. 12
    "Was it not at Taffy pulling had a fine time eating hard Molasses with unwashed hands. Did you ever pull any, when you had to spit on your hands to keep it from adhering to them?"
  - Annie ? to "Dear Sister Kate" w/envelope addressed to Kate Armentrout 1862 Feb. 8
    Family news and local gossip; "take good care of your health & tobacco"
  - Amanda C. Armentrout to "My once friend" [William F. Brand] w/envelope addressed to "Miss Amanda C. Armentrout, Greenville, Augusta County, Virginia" 1864 June 5
    "Oh dear one you are brooding over my sorrows & troubles & thinking how you will make me happy now let me beg of you dear one to forget me for awhile & think of yourself yes if I could come to you to night & fold my arms around your neck & pray for you I believe my earthly happiness would be compleat"
  - Robert [Robert B. Spillman], Office Chimborazo Hospital No. 3, Richmond, to "My dear Sweet Sister" 1864 Dec. 28
    In answer to her questions he provides information about his family and their ages [Note: a Robert B. Spillman was a member of Company C, 9th Virginia Cavalry, and was apparently listed in 1910 Census for Westmoreland County; see his letter of 2 September 1866]
  - Robert [Robert B. Spillman], Office Chimborazo Hospital, to "My Dear Sis Kate" w/envelope addressed to "Kate Armentrout" 1865 Jan. 12
    Is writing at eleven o'clock at night; "I Can't find words to Express Myself to night, I hope you will Excuse my brevity & I will promise to do better next time"
  - Robert [Robert B. Spillman], Chimborazo Hospital No. 3, Richmond, to "My dear Sister" w/envelope addressed to "Kate Armentrout" 1865 Jan. 29
    Rumor that the government is about to send commissioners to meet with the federal government to discuss "honorable terms for peace" [Hampton Roads Peace Conference, 3 February 1865]; signs this letter as "your affectionate & Ever loving Brother"
  - Robert [Robert B. Spillman], Fredericksburg, to "My Dear Sister Kate" 1865 Oct. 15
    "appreciate your true & unselfish friendship... but as for marrying indeed my friend that is something that I certainly should expect to do soon, my present situation... not admit of any thing of the sort were I to get married now I should think that I would be doing any lady justice in consequence of my embarrassing situation in life"; mentions Willie [William F. Brand]
  - Angus, Arbor Hill, Augusta County, Virginia, to "Dear Midie" [Amanda C. Armentrout] w/envelope 1866 April 8
    General news; asks if she received any April fools and sent any valentines
  - ACA, Rose Dale, to "My dear sweet brother" w/envelope addressed to William F. Brand, Alone [Mills], Rockbridge, Virginia 1866 July 6
    "I received your very dear letter several weeks ago & can say some part of it made me very happy"; calls recipient "Willie"; religious sentiment
  - ACA, Rose Dale, to "My dear friend" w/envelope addressed to WFB, Alone Mills, Rockbridge County 1866 July 23
    "I have been waiting for a letter from you but have waited in vain have come to the conclusion that you have forgotten me or must perhaps changed all again ha ha if so Willie let me know"; urges him to visit her
  - ACA, Rose Dale, to "My dear friend" [William F. Brand] 1866 July 29
    "Willie you wish a [relic?] you have loved me... not doubt that but your affection have changed & if you wish to be free again & I can hold they pure noble heart bind it to one that is so impure as mine for I have been the cause of your being unhappy"
  - ACA to "My dear friend" w/envelope addressed to WFB, Alone Mills, Rockbridge County 1866 Aug. 17
    Concludes with a poem: "Come back, Oh come! The past shall be as cloud forever removed.. ."
  - Robert B. Spillman, S farm, Westmoreland County, Virginia, to "My Dear Sister Kate" w/envelope endorsed "Oak Grove, VA./Sep 10/66" 1866 Sept. 2
    discusses the Christian character of their correspondence; wants to hear from her if she is still alive
  - Kate A. Brand [ACA], Rose Dale to "My Dear Willie" w/envelope addressed to William F. Brand, Alone Mills, Rockbridge County 1866 Oct. 7
    Complains he has not written to her; discusses the weather and crops; "my love is so strong that it makes me thus"; this is the first existent letter which she signs as "your ever true & loving wife Kate A. B[rand]"
  - Robert B. Spillman, S farm, Westmoreland County, Virginia, to "My Dear Sister" 1866 Oct. 13
    Was glad to her from her; general news
  - : ACA ["Midie/Kate"], Rose Dale, to "My dear friend" [William F. Brand] 1867 Sept. 1
    has just returned from visiting her friend Rachel; mentions Natural Bridge; today is her birthday
  - Kate A. Brand [ACA], Rose Dale, to "My dear dear husband" w/envelope addressed to William F. Brand, Alone Mills, Rockbridge County 1867 Nov. 17
    Has been ill; misses him; describes herself as a wayward child
- William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout 1861-1867
  - William F. Brand, Harpers Ferry, to ("Dear Cate") Amanda Catherine Armentrout, Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1861 April 25
    describes Harpers Ferry as dull; his company [Company E, 5th Virginia Infantry] has been presented a secession flag by Miss Fannie Lincoln
  - WFB, Harpers Ferry, to "Dear Kate" 1861 May 4
    has enlisted for duration of war which he expects will be three or four years; George W. Fitch [1835-1899] of the company sends his love
  - WFB, Harpers Ferry, Camp Bolivar, to "Dear Kate" 1861 May 25
    20,000 soldiers stationed near here including Alabamians and Mississippians and two of his uncles; mentions Union occupation of Alexandria and two shooting deaths [of Alexandria hotel keeper James Jackson and Union Colonel Elmer Ellsworth, 24 May 1861] because of the tearing down of a Confederate flag; reference to state election to confirm Virginia's secession--all but two members of the Augusta Grays voted for secession; the captain encouraged underage members to vote anyway: "Fifteen or twenty of us was not old enough to vote but our Captain told us to vote if we could & everyone voted [WFB, age twenty, was legally ineligible to vote]... one of our lowlife men talked like he would oppose our votes and the gentlemen was about to get himself the business he got so bad scared that he went and voted for secession"
  - WFB, Martinsburg, Berkeley County, to "Dear Kate," w/envelope addressed to Mrs. Kate Brand [his mother] 1861 June 23
    mentions visit of her friend John P. Lightner; promises to whip the bloodthirsty demons of the North
  - WFB, Winchester, to [ACA] w/envelope 1861 July 13
    drilling and guard duty; encloses poem "I Dreamed of The [Thee]"
  - WFB, Centreville, Fairfax County, to "Dear Kate" w/envelope 1861 Aug. 10
    argument involving his brother John [John W. Brand, 1842-1923] and Tom Graham [perhaps James W. T. Graham, ?-1892] has disrupted breakfast and caused a fight among them, Graham confined to a guardhouse; regiment reviewed by Prince Napoleon [Prince Napoléon-Jérôme, 1822-1891; born Napoléon-Joseph-Charles-Paul Bonaparte]; describes the battle of First Bull Run [First Manassas, 21 July 1861], became separated from his regiment and found himself fighting with the 4th Alabama Infantry
  - WFB, Centreville, to "Dear Friend Kate" w/envelope 1861 Sept. 12
    Is trying to get a furlough; James Trotter [James W. B. Trotter, ?-1864] failed to get a furlough to visit his father before he died
  - WFB, Camp Harmon, Centreville, Fairfax County, to "My Dear Kate" 1861 Sept. 15
    "No one can tell the pleasure that it affords a poor soldier on receiving a letter from his friends & acquaintances. It enlivens his mind and makes him energetic in performing his duties"; John Plunkett [John H. Plunkett, 1836-1885] questioned Union prisoners captured near Arlington Heights by Colonel Stuart's cavalry [Jeb Stuart, 1833-1864]; says rebel flags are waving right under Old Abe's [Abraham Lincoln] nose; "Thare are three men walking up and down our regiment carrying thare knapsacks as a punishment for thare misconduct. I would just as leave be shot"; wants very much to see her and pledges eternal love
  - WFB, Centreville, to "Dear Kate" 1861 Oct. 4
    mentions Samuel B. Fitch [?-1876] and his troubles with his sweetheart; regiment on picket duty last week and could see the Potomac River and the Capitol dome
  - WFB, Winchester, to "Dearest Kate" 1861 Nov. 13
    regrets news of the deaths of two women; his brother John has returned from a Richmond hospital [typhoid fever]; account of regiment's travel by train to Strasburg; officers' refusal to obey orders in dispute over campsites
  - WFB, Winchester, to "Dear Kate" [damaged, several words missing] 1861 Dec. 29
    return of William H. Brownlee [1841-1862] to camp after his furlough to Washington County; mention of General Richard Brooke Garnett's [1817-1863] orderly; describes Christmas dinner (with turkey)
  - WFB, Camp Sleepy Creek, to "Dear Kate," Lacy Springs, Rockbridge County, w/envelope 1862 Jan. 10
    hard marching and capture of prisoners at Bath in Morgan County [January 1, 1862, preliminary of Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson's Romney Campaign]
  - WFB, Winchester, to "Dear Kate," Lacy Springs, Rockbridge County, w/envelope 1862 March 4
    the regiment has left Camp Zollicoffer and government property being moved to Strasburg; he has enlisted as a regular for the war's duration and looks for God's protection for "he is able to save in the darkest hours of peril"; regret her brother did not reenlist [three Armentrout brothers served with the 5th Virginia during the war: Jacob, James, and John]
  - WFB to "Friend Kate," Lexington, w/envelope 1862 April 6
    company has been reorganized and he lists officers: Captain James W. Newton [1838-1896], Lieutenant Charles W. Grills [?-1862], David F. Eckard [1836-1914]; account of the battle of First Kernstown [March 23, 1862; during Stonewall Jackson's Valley Campaign] and describes the death of fellow soldier Robert F. Grass (shot through the head); 800 members in the regiment as of this date
  - WFB, Moton's Ford, to "Dear Friend" [ACA], [this is a photocopy of an original letter which is not present] 1862 April 23
    eleven members of the regiment have been sent to the hospital; camp news, prayer meeting led by "a good old Methodist preacher"
  - WFB, near Charles Town, to "Dear Kate," Greenville, Augusta County, w/envelope 1862 May 29
    account of the battle of Winchester [first battle of Winchester, May 25, 1862]; the regiment has been attacking the enemy since the 23rd [battle of Front Royal; Jackson's Valley Campaign], thousands of prisoners; local residents cheered the Confederate troops after the battle; for the first time the troops cheered General Charles S. Winder [1829-1862], usually they did not like him "because he is so strict"
  - WFB, camp near Liberty Mills, to "Dear Kate," Greenville, w/envelope 1862 July 25